Finding Aid for Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems records, 1901-1957
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems records 1901-1957
Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems.
852013 Bj 2; UBJl
Formerly the Anti-Saloon League of Ohio. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, financial reports, manuscripts of temperance plays, quiz book contest materials, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
16 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The record group was placed on deposit by the organization (donor no. 4754 ) in July 1969.
The record group is open to research.
Portions of the records have been microfilmed in 1977 as part of a joint project of the Michigan Historical Collections (now the Bentley Historical Library), the Ohio Historical Society, and the Woman's Christian Temperance Union.
From its beginning in 1893, the Anti-Saloon League worked effectively within Ohio for passage of prohibition legislation and for the election of "dry" candidates to the state legislature. The influence of the Ohio League was felt beyond the state level, with many of its leaders going on to hold offices in the national organization. Among the more prominent of these men were Howard Hyde Russell, Wayne B. Wheeler and Purley A. Baker.
In 1893, the executive committee of the Oberlin Temperance Alliance accepted Russell's ideas for organizing an Ohio Anti-Saloon League (A.S.L.) and agreed to provide early financing. State headquarters were opened in Columbus with Russell serving as the League's first superintendent.
The Ohio Anti-Saloon League was considered an effective temperance organization, and Russell received many requests for information. The Ohio League became the model for other state anti-saloon leagues, and workers from those states went to Ohio for training. In 1895, the Ohio League and the District of Columbia League joined together to organize the state Leagues into the National Anti-Saloon League--later renamed the Anti-Saloon League of America. Even with this overlap in ideas and leadership and with the location of national headquarters in nearby Westerville, Ohio, the Ohio and national Leagues eventually developed a relationship little different from that of any other state and the national group. The Anti-Saloon League of America focused on federal prohibition legislation while the state Leagues were more concerned with state legislation and elections.
During the 1920's, the League concentrated on enforcing the Eighteenth Amendment through educating citizens as well as prosecuting and jailing liquor law offenders. Frequent law enforcement conventions were held to maintain enthusiasm for prohibition and to improve enforcement practices. The Ohio League canvassed voters and candidates for their sentiment on the temperance question and worked hard to keep a majority of dry legislators in the state assembly.
During early 1933 the state set up the mechanism whereby repeal of the Eighteenth Amendment would take place. Following the resolution of the United States Congress proposing the Amendment to repeal Prohibition, the Ohio Legislature, in March, 1933, enacted the Mosier-Lawrence Act which provided for a convention of 52 delegates, elected at large by the people of Ohio, to ratify the amendment.
The League did what little it could to elect dry delegates, but, in November, 1933, the Ohio convention adopted the 21st Amendment for repeal of prohibition. Though the Ohio Anti-Saloon League was never able to regain the support it had earlier been capable of organizing, it did continue its temperance and prohibition work by presenting temperance plays and continuing with its "Quiz Book Contest" programs.
The organization later changed its name to the Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems.
The records of the Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Miscellaneous printed material, press releases, etc.; Financial and other materials; Newspaper clippings; Dramatic productions; Quiz Contest; Chronological files; Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Elections--Ohio--1928.; Elections--Ohio--1932.; Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems.; Ohio--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Prohibition--Ohio.; Temperance--Ohio.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alcoholism.; Anti-saloon League of Ohio.; Diseases.; Ohio Council on Alcohol Problems.; Slums.; Temperance--United States.
Contributors:
Anti-Saloon League of America.; Anti-saloon League of Ohio.; Ohio Dry Federation.; Temperance League of Ohio.
Genre Terms:
Glass phototransparencies.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1915-1938, 18 folders (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous printed material, press releases, etc.
  - Undated 1902-1914, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1917-1947, 13 folders (Box 2)
- Financial and other materials
  - Financial reports 1919-1953
    - Financial reports 1919-1928 (Box 3)
    - Financial reports 1929-1953 (Box 3)
  - Mimeograph work orders 1932-1937 (Box 3)
  - Minutes of the Ohio Dry Federation 1917-1922 (Box 3)
- Newspaper clippings
  - Undated 1932-1935, 6 folders (Box 3)
- Dramatic productions
  - Material for temperance plays 1932-1938, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Casts of players for play, "Prisoner at the Bar" 1937 (Box 4)
  - Casts of players for play, "The Tiger" 1937-1939, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Handbills and posters for temperance plays (Box 4)
- Quiz Contest
  - 1931-1932, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - 1931-1932, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1937-1938, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - 1940-1942, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - 1943-1944, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1945-1946, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - 1946-1947, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - 1946-1947, 8 folders (Box 8)
  - 1947-1948, 1 folders (Box 8)
  - 1947-1948, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - 1949-1950, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1951-1952, 4 folders (Box 9)
- Chronological files
  - Youth Temperance Convention, Columbus, Ohio 1932 (Box 9)
  - Olympians and organization of participants in the Quiz Book Contest 1933-1934 (Box 9)
  - Candidates for office 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Schedules of speakers 1940, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - General materials
    - 1942-1943 (Box 10)
    - 1944, 6 folders (Box 10)
    - 1944, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - 1946, 9 folders (Box 11)
    - 1946, 1 folders (Box 12)
    - 1947, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - 1948, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - 1948, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - 1949, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - 1950, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - 1951, 1 folders (Box 13)
    - 1951, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - 1952, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - 1953, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - 1954, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - 1955, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - 1955, 2 folders (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous
  - Ledger concerning the Toledo canvass 1941 (Box 15)
  - Account book (receipts) 1945-1950 (Box 15)
  - Account book (disbursements) 1944-1947 (Box 15)
  - Copies of bills 1942-1952, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings 1946-1948 (Box 15)
  - Income tax records 1937-1944, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Miscellanea 1932-1957, undated, 3 folders (Box 15)
- Photographs
  - Glass slides 1901-1921, 200 slides in 3 file boxes approximate (Box 16)
    (slides probably used in lectures on the problems of alcohol, including slides of statistical charts, temperance movement prints and posters, and views of slums and alcohol-related diseases)
  - Photographs 1918-1948, 1 envelopes (Box 16)
  - Convention gatherings (Folder UBJl)